<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Interrogatories vpon which ... churchwardens shalbe charged, for searche, of al such things as now be amysse.]</title>
            <title>Visitation articles. 1558</title>
            <author>Church of England.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1558</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 19 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00120</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10117</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112645</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847891</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847891</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12955</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00120)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12955)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 241:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[Interrogatories vpon which ... churchwardens shalbe charged, for searche, of al such things as now be amysse.]</title>
                  <title>Visitation articles. 1558</title>
                  <author>Church of England.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Robart Caly, wythin the precinct of Christes Hospitall,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>The .vi. day of Aprill. M. D. LVIII. Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum] [1558]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title from STC; imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Copies differ; in this copy the "A" of signature A2 is under "al" of "allowed"--STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; lacks title page.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Visitations, Ecclesiastical --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="articles">
            <pb facs="tcp:12955:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12955:1"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="i."/>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt if there be within theyr pariſhe a
Parſon, Vicar or Curat, reſident continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie vpon his benefice and cure,
doyng his dutye there as he is bound to do in al things, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in
preaching, ſaying Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tins, Maſſe, and Euenſonge at due tyme,
chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtening, viſiting the ſicke, buryeng, and doynge al other ſuch
like, and whether he hath ſolemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized Matrimonie, the bannes not duly before
aſked, or haue celebrated the ſame, or other di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine ſeruice in any
oratorie or priuate chappell not allowed nor licenced ſo to do by thordinary
or other ſufficient auctoritye in that behalfe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="ii."/> Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whether the ſaid Parſon, Vicar, or
Cui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rat, haue been heretofore maried or no, &amp; if he continue with his woman
or either of them ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piciouſlye doo reſorte to other.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="iii."/> Item whether within the ſaid pariſh
there be openly or ſecretly any maried prieſt, or any wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man heretofore
maried to a prieſt, and whither they be ſuſpected of any euell rule and
euel con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation or no, and who be noted to be the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porters,
maynteiners, fauourers or bearers of them in any wiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="iiii."/> Item whither ther be within the ſaid
pariſh any that doth maintayne or vphold the opinion that prieſtes and
religious perſones may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullye be maryed and continue together.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="v."/> Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whether there be within your pariſh any
prieſte that taketh vpon hym to ſerue the cure, not being before examined
and allowed thereto <pb facs="tcp:12955:2"/>by thordinary, and
whither the ſaid prieſt hath in the tyme of the late ſciſme here in the
realme preached hereſy or euil doctrine, and not recan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the ſame, or
doth not now preache and ſette forth the true doctrine of the catholike
church, and alſo pray for the three eſtates of the catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like churche, and
eſpeciallye for the Kynge and Quenes Maieſties, and alſo whither prayinge
for the thyrd eſtate, they do name Purgatorye or no.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="vi."/> Item whither there be within the ſayde
pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe any that do obſtinately perſiſt and ſtande in any hereſie
or hereticall opinion,or be ſuſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of erronious and falſe doctrine or
a fauorer, mainteiner or aider of any erronious or hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call perſon or
perſones, or of any hereſies or he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall opinions, or noughty
doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="vii."/> Item whether you knowe or haue heard ſay
of any perſon or perſones within your ſaid pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, that hath kept, or
at this preſent doth kepe any hereticall, noughtye, or ſedicious erronious
booke or bookes, eſpecially engliſh teſtamentes or Bibles falſely
tranſlated, ſecretlye or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, and whither ye haue any
ſuſpectes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="viii."/> Item whyther ye knowe or haue hearde of
anye Prynters or Bookeſellers wythin youre Pariſhe that hathe ſolde, or
nowe dothe ſell or keepe anye the ſayde hereticall, nawghtye, or
ſedicious booke or bookes, letters or wrytyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and whyther ye haue anye
ſuſpectes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="ix."/> Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whyther ye knowe or haue hearde ſaye
<pb facs="tcp:12955:2"/>of anye perſon or perſones within
your Pariſhe that wyllynglye or obſtinatelye dothe neglecte or refuſe to
make theyr confeſſion to the Prieſt, and to receyue abſolution and
penaunce at hys hande for hys offences, or obſtinatelye or wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynglye doo
refuſe to receyue the Sacrament of the Aultare, or extreme Vnction, in
extreme daunger of ſyckeneſſe, or to heare Maſſe, or to come to hys
Paryſhe Churche, or refuſe to go on Proceſſion, or to take Holywater,
or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe doo myſuſe them ſelues in breakynge the Rytes and
Ceremonyes of the Catholyque Churche, ſpeciallye in faſtynge on the Ember
dayes and other dayes by the Churche ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye appoynted, or in prayinge,
or other ſuche lyke.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="x."/> Item whyther ye knowe or haue hearde of anye
perſon or perſones wythin your Paryſhethat haue murmured, grudged or
ſpoken direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye or indirectlye agaynſte the Maſſe, or other
eccleſiaſticall ſeruice, vſed or commaunded in the Churche, or
againſte anye Sacramentes or Sacramentalles of the ſame, as holye breade,
holy water, aſhes, palmes, creping to the croſſe, holye Oyle, and
Chriſme, bearynge of Palmes or Candelles, buryinge of the deade, or praying
for them, ſpeciallye in ſayinge of Diriges and Commendations, or in
vſinge anye other lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable or Godlye Ceremonye or vſage of the
Churche.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xi."/> Item whither there be within your Paryſhe
anye that dothe fauoure, or is ſuſpected to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept or receyue any noughty
perſon or perſones. <pb facs="tcp:12955:3"/>eſpecially
to rede the engliſh ſeruice, vſed in the time of king Edwarde the
ſixte, or the booke of Communion, or anye booke prohibited or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bydden to
be redde or taught, or to ſet forth any noughtye opinion or doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xii."/> Item whither there be within the ſayde
pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh any priuie lectures or ſermons, or other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſes, or anye
vnlawfull conuenticles or aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xiii."/> Item whether there be within the ſayde
pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe any, that at the ſacring time of the Maſſe dothe hange downe
theyr heades, or hyde them ſelues behinde pillers, or turneth away their
fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or departeth out of the church, becauſe they woulde not looke vpon
the bleſſed ſacrament of the Aultare.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xiiii."/> Item whether ye knowe or haue hearde
ſaye of any perſone or perſones within your pariſhe that haue committed
Lollardie, as in eatyng of fleſhe at dayes and times forbydden or
other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, practiſing or allowinge anye the opinions of the Lollardes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xv."/> Item whither there be within the ſayde
pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh any perſon, man, woman, or childe, being of ſufficient age and
diſcretion that can not ſaye theyr <hi>Pater noſter, Aue Maria,</hi> and
the Crede.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xvi."/> Item whither there be within your pariſh
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſchole maſter or ſcolemaſtreſſe that do teach Children to
rede, write, ſing, or play, not beyng firſt examined and admitted thereunto
by thor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie or his ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t deputie, and whither the ſaid
ſcolemaſter and ſcolemaiſtreſſe be ſound in religion, and of
honeſt lyuing and diſcrete beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, <pb facs="tcp:12955:3"/>cauſing
theyr ſcholers to faſt, to praye, to come to the church, and to do theyr
duties ther, ſpecially in hearing Maſſe and other diuine ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, and
whither they teache them to helpe the Prieſt to Maſſe, and to ſaye
their <hi>Pater noſter,</hi> the <hi>Aue Maria,</hi> and the Crede with
<hi>De profundis</hi> for all Chriſten ſoules, and whither the ſcholes,
eſpecially being commen be faithfully and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently kept or no.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xvii."/> Item whither there be within the ſayde
pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe any that do abſent them ſelues willynglie from the churche,
looſinge Mattins, Maſſe, or Euenſong, or anye parte thereof, and
whyther there be any ſuſpectes vpon Sondayes or holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daies colorable to
abſent them ſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr owne pariſh church, and to go into the
countrie vnder pretence to ſee theyr houſe and the ſtate of theyr thynges
there, hearynge diuine ſeruice in no place.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xviii."/> Item whether you knowe or haue hearde of
any in your pariſhe, that haue bene, or is a ſcold or a ſlaunderous
perſon of his neighbours, or a ſower of diſcorde and debate betwene
partye and partie, eſpecially betwene man and wyfe, or the parentes and theyr
children, or any ſuche like, or that hath inuented, bruted, or ſet forth
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny rumours, falſe or ſedicious tales, or ſclaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, or of any makers,
bryngers in, byers, ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, readers, keepers, or conueyers of anye
vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull letters, bookes, or wrytinges, ſtirringe or prouoking ſedicion
within thys realme, or of any theyr ayders, counſaylours, abbettors,
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curers or mayntayners therein.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12955:4"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xix."/> Item whither ye know or haue heard of any
within the ſayde pariſh that haue geuen occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to moue or ſturre vp
any deuiſion, ſtrife, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention or ſedition, eſpecially betwene the
king and Quenes maieſties and their Subiectes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xx."/> Item whether ye knowe or haue heard ſaye of
any concelementes, contempts, conſpiracies, falſe rumors, tales,
ſedicious, miſbehauiours, ſlaunderous woordes, bruted or ſpred by anye
perſon or perſones againſt the King and Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Maieſties, or either of
them, or agaynſt the quiet rule and gouernaunce of theyr ſubiectes or
realmes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xxi."/> Item whither the Patrones and other ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
aduowſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of benefices haue ſincerly, tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and iuſtly preſented in
due time, and in good order an able Clerke to the benefice vacant, not
ſuffring the ſaid benefice long to remaine with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Paſtor or
Curate.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xxii."/> Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whither you know of anye Patrones or
other, hauing aduowſons that haue directly or indirectly practiſed,
couenanted or agreed with any perſon or perſones before the preſentation
or after, to haue anye ſumme of money for the ſame, or any other profite,
commoditie or plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in anye wiſe vnder anye colour or conuey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce,
what ſo euer it be.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xxiii."/> Item whither ye know any Patrones or
o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,hauing ſuch aduowſons or any other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone that of his owne
priuate authoritie and pleaſure haue pulled downe any Church, chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, or
other eccleſiaſtical buildinge, or haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away the lead, belies,
ornamentes, goodes, <pb facs="tcp:12955:4"/>or landes of the
ſaid places, or anye of them, or ſpoyled anye of the ſame, or haue
conuerted the tithes, profites, commodities, reuenewes, and poſſeſſions
of anye of the ſame to his owne pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate and prophane vſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xxiiii."/> Item whether ye knowe or haue hearde of
any Parſon, Vicar, or other, hauing eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call promotion, that
hathe made alienation of ſuche thinges as perteyned to his Parſonage,
Vicarege, or ſpirituall promotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or let the ſame to farme, without
licence of his Ordinarye, and if he ſo in anye the premiſſes haue done,
what it was, when it was, and by what authority or warrant it was done.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xxv."/> Item whither the churche of your pariſhe
be nowe vacante or no, who is the patrone therof, how long it hath bene vacant,
who doth receiue the tythes, oblations, and other commodities thereof, during
the ſayd vacation, and by what authoritie, and in what eſtate the ſayde
churche as in.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xxvi."/> Item whither within the ſaide pariſhe
there be any woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that doth exerciſe thoffice or rome of a Midwyfe, not
beyng before examined and admitted thereto by thordinary or his ſufficient
deputy, or whither there be any woman, hauing bene a prieſts wife or
ſuſpect of hereſy, that is a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon keper of women lying in childbed or
no.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xxvii."/> Item whither the ſaid Midwife haue
here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore bene, and now is catholike, faithfull, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete, ſober, and
diligent, ready to helpe euerye woman trauelyng with childe, aſwel the poore
as the riche.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12955:5"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xxviii."/> Item whither the ſaide woman or any
other comming to ſuch trauelling do vſe any Witche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft, charmes, or
vnlawful praiers or inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, or do omit or alter the lawdable rytes and
ceremonies accuſtomed and vſed of antiquitie.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xxix,"/> Item whither the ſaid midwife or other
wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man denieth or letteth the newe borne childe to be brought to the church,
and to be duly, reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently and orderlye baptiſed, and the mother to be duly
and accuſtomably purified.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xxx."/> Item whither any woman by them ſelues or
by the ſmiſtre counſell of other, haue after their own fantaſies
purified them ſelues or done any thing therein contrary to the law,
ordenaunce, and cuſtome of the catholike church.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xxxi."/> Item whither the Churchwardens of your
pariſhe haue and do prouide all thinges neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and requiſite to be
had in your church, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge as hathe bene accuſtomed wythin thys realme
of Englande, before the time of the late ſchiſme in the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xxxii."/> Item whither within your ſaid pariſhe
there be a roode and a roode loft, hauing the Images of Mary and Iohn, &amp;
lightes before the ſame, and whither in the Lent ſeaſon there be a
coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring for the ſaide Crucifixe decentlye prouided, and whither there be
any lightes vpon the high Aultare, and whither there be an Image of the patrone
of the church or no.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xxxiii."/> Item whither there be any Inuentary made
and kept of the church goodes, and a boke con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the regeſtringe of
thoſe that are bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, maried, or buryed.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12955:5"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xxxiiii."/> Item whither the beſtimentes for the
prieſts and other miniſters, and al the ornamentes for and about the altar,
be kept clene and ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repayred and mainteined, and whither there be
any thing lacking or no, and whither there be a comely pixe to kepe the
bleſſed ſacrament in &amp; vpon the high Aultar, and whither there be any
light burning before it, eſpecially in the time of diuine ſeruice, and
whither the bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be caryed decentlye and deuoutlye to the
ſicke, the Clerke goynge before the Prieſte in a ſurpleſſe with
lighte in his hand, and a litle ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cring bell ringing.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xxxv."/> Item whither the church or chauncel of your
pariſh be in ruine or decay, and in whoſe default or negligence the ſame
is.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xxxvi."/> Item whither there haue bene or be anye
le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacies or gyftes made for the repayrynge and mayntenaunce of your church, or
of high waies, finding of the poore, maryenge of poore May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, or anye
ſuche like, and the ſame not payde and aunſwered accordingly.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xxxvii."/> Item whither there be any man within your
pariſhe, that beſides his wyfe keepeth inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently any other woman, or
any woman which beſides her huſband taketh or vſeth with any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man,
or whither any man doth put awaye his wife, or any wyfe doth withdrawe her
ſelfe from her huſband, not beynge lawfullye before diuorſed, and beyng
lawfully diuorced, whither anye of the parties duringe the life of the other do
mary or no.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xxxviii."/> Item whyther ye knowe of anye man that
<pb facs="tcp:12955:6"/>hath two wiues liuing, or of anye
woman that hath two huſbandes lyuing, no lawful diuorce beyng made betwene
them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xxxix."/> Item whither you knowe of any vſurers,
or of any bawdes, man or woman, or of any other vicious and notable offendours
and breakers of Gods holye commaundementes, and of the godly orders, lawes, and
lawdable cuſtomes of the holy catholike church in any wiſe, eſpecially
vpon Embring or faſting dayes, or vpon Son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes or holydayes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xl."/> Item whither the church or churchyard haue
bene violated, poluted, or ſuſpended in any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of wayes, eſpecially
by effuſion of blood, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olently made or done in the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xli."/> Item whither anye dothe take vpon hym to
miniſtre the goodes of any that is deade before the Teſtament be proued, or
adminiſtration to him by thordinary dulye committed, or doth let the
Teſtament or laſt wyll in anye wyſe to be fulfilled.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xlii."/> Item whither ſuche as can not reade vpon
the booke, haue euerye one of theym a payre of beades, and doo vſe the ſame
deuoutlye and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xliii."/> Item whither anye Minſtrels or anye
other perſons do vſe to ſyng or ſay any ſonges or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that be
vncleane or vile, eſpeciallye againſt any of the.vii. Sacramentes, or
againſt any the rites and ceremonies of thys Churche of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, whyche is
a notable member of Chriſtes catholike churche.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xliiii."/> Item whither any do depraue or contempne
<pb facs="tcp:12955:6"/>the auctoritie or iuriſdiction of
the Popes holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, or the ſea of Rome, or do let the proceſſe of anye
Archbyſhoppe or Byſhoppe, or of anye of theyr deputies.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xlv."/> Item whither any playes or Interludes not
beyng firſt examined, allowed, and approued by thordinary, are vſed at any
tyme, eſpeciallye in the Lent, or vpon Sondaies or holydaies, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallye
at the tyme of diuine ſeruice, and why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any other vyle or lewde
paſtimes at any of the ſayde times, are in anye wyſe vſed or
accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xlvi."/> Item whither there be any that doth vſe
to bye &amp; ſel vpon the ſundayes or holydayes, or do vpon thoſe dayes
kepe open theyr ſhoppes, Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernes, Alehouſes, or victualyng houſes,
eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the time of diuine ſeruice,</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xlvii."/> Item whither ye haue procured or
conſented in any wyſe,that duryng anye part of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon made at Paules
Croſſe, there ſhoulde be
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rynging of belles, playing
of Children, cryinge or making lowde noyſe, rydinge of horſes, or
o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwyſe, ſo that the Preacher there, or his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience was troubled
thereby, and if ye haue not ſo procured or conſented, whither haue you yet
to the beſt and vttermoſte of your power ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uowred your ſelfe to let
ſuch ringinge, playeng, cryeng, and noyſe, that the ſaid Preacher might
the better doo his duty, and the audience be the better inſtructed and
edified.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="xlviii."/> Item whither ye do know, or crediblye
haue heard that within any part of the citye of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don there hath bene any
ſet tables kept for ſuch <pb facs="tcp:12955:7"/>as woulde
thyther reſorte to eate and drynke, and whither it be not vſed at the
ſaid tables to haue Diner and Supper vpon the Fryday and Embryng dayes, and
all other dayes, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well within the Lent time as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, or whither there
be at the ſaide tables any fleſh ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten at times pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="privilege">
            <pb facs="tcp:12955:7"/>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London by Robart Caly, wythin the precinct
of Chriſtes Hoſpitall.
<date>The .vi. day of Aprill. <hi>M.D.LVIII.</hi>
               </date>
            </p>
            <p>Cum priuilegio ad imprimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ſolum.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
